So d by 18 of mn star ve
So ve is the same as before
What I have done over here is
I have stolen away the periodicity part
So I say that I write another set of equations
Where I modify the mass
So that I can throw away a vector on the right hand side
This is a mathematical operation
How do you modify the mass?
There are two ways in which people modify the mass
One way is to actually do really complicated calculations
Which we will go into later
Once I have defined both notions of effective mass
And the other which is always in this
Measured mass
How would you measure it?
That's what we don't do
That's why we have kind of reduced this equation
We don't want to go to the pathway of the first equation
We are desperately trying to avoid that
Yes
An equation is made for a single electron
Or it's for the mole of electron?
This
This equation
Good question
This question is
The second equation is what I would call a statistical equation
It refers to the average electron
So you expect most electrons to follow this
In that sense of an average
And we can do statistical averaging
Because we are starting with a very very large number
Of 10 to the power 23 of those electrons
Which is
The requirement of statistics
N represents electron
N always represents electron
Sub n always represents electron
Okay so
Yeah
Sir what does direction define energy?
Well your velocity is in a particular direction right?
That was earlier also right?
I am coming to that
Coming to that
So
What is F periodic?
Huh?
F periodic
F periodic is gone
Where is F periodic?
That is the whole reason we consider to be effective mass
Oh okay
Okay
So what is the loss of simplicity?
The mass is no longer a scalar now
Let us think in a little bit
Because we removed the periodicity so
Mass is no longer a scalar
You are in R3
I will have to define a different mass for each direction
Because
Okay think about it this way
You are moving in that direction
You are moving in different directions
Has a different set of inertia associated with it
How do we understand mass?
There is more scattering here
I say okay I am not going to worry about scattering arising from periodic sources
I am just going to lump it up into my
In a measure of inertia in that direction
So that is a direction dependence
And this is what is known as a kinematic definition of effective mass
There is going to be a different definition
It is going to be slightly more complicated
Unrelated to this
But often leads to similar numbers
But not always
The reason we need to understand that
But M star is a vector
M star is not a vector
It is a tensor
So basically it is a 3 by 3 matrix in R3P
All the matrixes have all the matrix properties
Right but then there are also cross terms
So whenever we talk about matrices
We say that it is diagonalizable under certain terms
So that you know you have got 0 above 0 at the bottom upper triangular lower triangular
And then there are 3 scalars along the diagonal
Similar to the vector matrix what we have
But in this case you cannot throw away the cross terms
It depends upon what kind of matrix actually you have got
How does that matrix work?
How does it look like?
We are coming to that
That is the project that allows me to present something
Okay now let us shell the discussion for a bit
And let me go into aspects which talk about construction of the lattice in the first place
Because the second definition arises naturally from there
Okay silicon atom
Let us imagine a universe where a single silicon atom exists
Okay
Obviously we cannot exist in that universe
Because we are not obligated in that
The shell structure for silicon is 1s2, 2s2, 2p6, 3s2, 3p2
We have seen this since I don't know 11th grade or something
Let us count is that 14?
Yeah 4 plus 6 plus 4
So I have got these two
What are the red and the blue lines?
Anybody want to guess?
Values?
Singularity
Yes
Ground state and excited state
Because we have one single atom here
And the two atoms or rather you know the ion core is basically red
Which is at the bottom
And the signal electron which is free to move around is kind of shown schematically at the bottom
Okay
What is the red dot?
Red dot is the ion core
Basically 14 protons and a certain number of neutrons club together
What is the black dot?
Yeah that is the black dot
So what was the black?
The black dot is the electron that we are talking about right?
Oh
Huh?
Okay
The red core is essentially the nucleus of silicon
And the inner shell which don't participate in ground core
We don't care about
Everything except the valence shell
Valence shell is what we are interested in
Right?
Okay
Now let us now bring these two atoms closer to each other
I think you have seen in 11th grade what happens
Molecular orbital forms
Right?
And one of the properties of a molecular orbital are
That each energy level splits into two
Right?
Bonding and anti-bonding
The bonding being more stable and hence lower energy
So the ground state splits into two
Bonding and anti-bonding
And the excited state splits into two
So you have got four energy levels now
So two atoms brought together lead to four energy levels
I think we can start to see the beginning of a geometric sequence here
Sir
Yeah
Let us just consider one of the four energy levels
Just to simplify
It will be too complicated to write four different
Okay
Now let us see what these states look like
You have all seen this
Atomic orbitals and how they form you know
Molecular orbitals
So there is an anti-bonding orbital which consists of a node
On the line connecting the two atoms
Sorry anti-node
Anti-node right
Because that is where the probability density is the minimum
And the bonding orbital means that there is more effective sharing of the electron cloud
Which forms a covalent bond
Hence the term bonding
And hence there is a node there
So this is LCAOQ
Kind of remember linear combination of atomic orbitals
That picture
Now let us bring in the number three
What is the below part?
Below part yeah
So the below part is basically the energy levels of potential
So each of these carriers carries different energy
It is from the textbook
It is pretty silly to take pictures according to the textbook
So what is this?
Why is there a well here?
Huh?
I mean the below part
There are two iron cores right?
The potential energy heads towards infinity
As the electron gets closer
So those two wells now that is in between
That is you know basically a shallow barrier
Okay
Now let us bring in the number three
Yeah
So you had these four states adding in two more
Eight
So let us see what happens
Right
So each splits into two again
Now let us carry this process forward
More atoms leads to more energy levels splitting
And if you have molar atoms
You can see this process you know
Going forth
And you basically get a quasi-continuum
Which is
Has a large separation in between
So this is your band gap
So conduction band on the top
Which is constructor and bonding orbitals
And the Williams band on the bottom
Constructing of your bonding orbitals
Okay
Okay let us go back
So more atoms lead to more energy levels splitting
And you notice that
You know
The way these gaps are opening up
As a result of that addition process
If I have a large enough
You know of course we cannot sit here and
Go to four, five, six and count up to ten
Partly three that is like silly
But this is what it results in
And these are bands
And the difference between the energy level
Of the lowest anti-bonding orbital
And the highest bonding orbital
Is known as the band gap
Mind you I have not defined what the x-coordinate is
Which is a different story
Only the bicoordinate
X-coordinate
Yeah it does
Massively
In some sense understanding basic semi-character
Is about understanding the x-coordinate
Yeah
You will figure out in a moment why
Any questions
So what
So there are more energy levels above this
Uh
So essentially what is an anti-bonding orbital
Where electrons don't have to go
Because they have got higher energy
So even from basic principles we can argue that
Everything in blue over here is unoccupied
Electrons don't have to go there
So they don't have to come home
In organic semiconductors for instance
That is the term that is used
Highest occupied molecular orbital or HOMO
And lowest unoccupied molecular orbital
That is LUMO
But LUMO and HOMO are sharp levels in organics
These are bands
There is a difference
Because in molecular systems
You don't have very very strong interactions
Between different various molecules
That wonder why they interact with each other
And hence as a result bands don't form
Okay everybody understand where the band gap now comes from?
No
Silicon forms covalent bonds
Gemini forms covalent bonds
Most of the materials you come across
Kalium nitrate whatever
Forms covalent bonds
Bands of this nature
Or something very close to this will form
But if we talk about organic semiconductors
There is a different breed of semiconductors altogether
ALQ3 for instance
It is a complicated
You know
Are you capsized with a name which I don't care to remember or repeat?
You just understand what that name is
When you are writing down a paper
Put it once in a bracket and then forget about it
Is that kind of a name?
I am not a chemist
Those interactions between molecules and molecules are not covalent
They are wonder walls
Which means there are weak interactions
Weak interactions means less of energy splitting
Remember
We have to bring atoms very very close to each other
For this energy splitting argument to work
If they remain far apart from each other
Then the perturbation of one atom on the other
Is going to be very very weak
And as a result the splitting will not occur
So that's why bands don't form in organic semiconductors
So they basically behave as if they are like
I would say the electrons move through them
In a way of hopping transport
So one side it has an escape probability
It's like a trap
Then go to the next trap
So unsurprisingly the conductivity in organic molecules is off
Much weaker than traditional semiconductors of this kind
But anyhow that's what you are going to learn in organic
Sir
Yeah
Sir so the valence band is essentially a bonding orbital
Just like a continuous
It forms a continuum because I got into it 23 years ago
Of course there are subbands inside
And we will learn about subbands later
When we need to
Because there is internal structure to these bands also
But we will come to that a bit later
Okay
So in keeping with the earlier terminology
Valence electrons live in valence band
That they are tightly bound
The K, L, M, shell etc
While the conduction electrons which are relatively free to move around
Live in the conduction band
And the business of understanding how much is in each
Will come from statistics
So we will get to that later
So another thing
This is now color convention
When it comes to doping
I will be using similar colors here
N is always represented as blue
P is always represented as red
And you will understand why in a moment
Obviously crystal structure arises from minimization of energy
All of you have seen this plot most likely
Right
Two atoms coming together
And you know what is the energy of the electrons
You know that are bound to that
So for hydrogen for instance
This energy minimization process leads to a bond length of around 74 picometers
For silicon that number is different
We have previously arrived at what 5 angstroms or something like that
Something like that
So each element has its own particular value
And this is now the silicon band structure
This is from your textbook again
So it divides up
So you see
What is the x axis here?
Anybody want to guess?
Distance between the two atoms
Yeah
So if I constructed a virtual silicon crystal
Where let's say the virtual is well advised over here
Where the distance between neighboring silicon atoms was not 5 angstroms
But was 10 angstroms
Then my band structure would look different
This is where real silicon exists
This dashed line
If I go further here then it would look a little bit like this
But it's virtual because nature does not construct that material for us
Because we have no way of keeping silicon atoms in any silicon crystal further apart than 5 angstroms
Because of lower energy
Yeah
Every system seeks its lowest energy
So it's not going to stay there
But this is basically more like a mathematical model
So what are those lines?
Like at one point you have two lines
Yeah
So these are what are known as sub-bands
Not very well defined here
So that is why most people find this figure coming so soon
The text local is a bit indigestible
But I'm just telling you
That there are two concepts here
States and electrons
At least we can agree on that
States refers to an electron can exist here
It doesn't mean that it will exist there
It can exist here
While on the other hand
An electron is an electron
It's either there or it's not there
It's a binary choice
So it's like the bonding electrons are there and electrons are there
In the anti-bonding also electrons can be there
But they're not usually there because they're anti-bonding orbitals to start with
Like if I have a surplus of electrons then it will be there
You'll have to be more clear about what you mean by surplus of electrons
I mean like for silicon there are only 14 electrons
So 4 electrons take place in this bonding-anti-bonding
If I had say a different atom with say 18 electrons
It'll also have a different band structure
For the same
If it had the same band structure then it would be okay
But again then we're talking about a virtual material
Yeah
Okay
So why is it always an integer multiple?
Because we count electrons
There's no such thing as 1.3 electrons
So it's an integer multiple of the number of electrons
I mean if you have zero electrons how can you have three minor states in the total state?
See four n states means that there are that many places for electrons to go set
But they're not sitting there at present
Do these states have to be equal in the conduction band and valence band or are they different?
They can be different, depends on your bandwidth
It depends on how many bonding and what is the energy level difference between bonding and anti-bonding and etc.
Again multiple depends completely
But what is the use of this diagram if we cannot create such a diagram?
The use of this diagram is for you to get an early flavour of that
The concept of a state being available and the concept of an electron actually populating that state are two different ideas
We will based on, you know, driven or motivated by this diagram calculate the number of states available
And also the correspondence that is needed to populate those states
The combination of the two will give us certain important quantities
And that we want to possibly by next next lecture
Sir but in this diagram the only part of the diagram that we ever will really work with is the
The dashed line, the rest are all virtual materials
The dashed line, the vertical dashed line, that is real silicon, the rest is all virtual silicon
Right? Okay
Sir how from the graph are we integrating this four n and three n at any specific point?
Pardon?
Yeah?
Like if you take any point on this line, how are you integrating that?
Okay there will be two n states, okay there will be four n states or something
Because we are talking about fermions, right?
Electrons up spin and down spin
Yes
So two states
No I mean if you take any random point on this
Yes
Like there is no like order in this thing
It would be like a state and then there will be something less than a state as you go along
This is a continuum right?
This is a continuum
Yes
So it could be anywhere in here right?
No I mean you like they say it is four n states and then after that eight n states and then two n states
So there is no order, so how are you pinpointing the number of
Because that arises from silicon matter
It is a result of a calculation, yes
Sir also is there any concept of kind of on purpose pushing or pulling the silicon atoms
In different distances for ideal value?
Okay now you have raised an important question that you didn't mean to
Strain silicon
Like if I take silicon and I grow it on a substrate
Which is lattice mismatched
What will that do?
Mismatched as an exfoliator
Like it either has a lattice constant larger than five or smaller than five
Compressive or tensile strain
Which means that I will be constructing one of these virtual silicons there
But at least within certain number of monolayers
Because I know what happens when I go further away from the interface
We already discussed it actually
There it basically relaxes to bulk whether through formation dislocations or not
Because
Because silicon you cannot force a bulk
Like a large piece of silicon into becoming virtual silicon of some sort
It will only mean certain number of layers that is impacted by that
Yes
Sir in the previous diagram you actually
You don't have to go back sir
Like when we had bonding and anti-bonding
There was a lower line for bonding electrons
And the upper line
So the two lines for the actual spacing that we have
Where we have force n states
And force n electrons
Those are for the bonding ones
Then there is the bandgap
And then the upper two are for the anti-bonding ones
Yeah so force n states and zero electrons
Yeah
Mind you force n states and zero electrons is something that would occur at absolute zero
Where there is no energy available for the electrons to go up the production band
You will discover that in like a couple of slides but I am just putting it out here
In this graph here you can see what is a virtual silicon and what is a real silicon
Dash line is the real silicon
The vertical dash line
That is it
Because that is the lattice distance at which silicon condenses
There is no other distance
But there are three dash lines
Oh they are just reference lines
They were just showing okay that in that particular period there is no gap
Pardon
I think you are referring to this neck over here right
Yeah
So this is also a virtual silicon
But importantly there is no bandgap
So that is why it is indicated in that
Sir is there
What is the use for virtual silicon?
I just mentioned
You got a straight layer of silicon
You will have to go
That is how the moment created
But are there like
Oh yes
The effective mass for instance is different for straight silicon
You might need it for some application
What about for a very small layer like say 10-20 layers of silicon
Is it useful practically like can you build and you know
I would say that almost all the modern devices basically they rely almost critically on those 10-20 layers
The bulk does not matter
Sir so the casual speed will be different in a screened or compressed silicon obviously
They will have different mobilities different bandgap everything is different
So which one actually has a faster speed is there like a general input or
No
So for instance it depends upon whether the scattering in that particular direction changes enough so as to go below the bulk silicon scattering or not
Will depend upon the material how it is trained by how much it is trained
And whether there are any dipole-dipole interactions because if the underlying material is polar
It will have an influence it will lead to dipole scattering also
So it is a complex question depends on each system
Sir so we can does that actually math exist like is it
Math is very hard
See this is a case of where math is extremely hard but experiments are relatively easy
And importantly they get you the result you want
So yeah
Sir so maybe we can come up with a theory to explain this
It depends
So how are these states defined there and I am not looking at that what is that important state
But if I didn't show it to you you will understand exactly
Sir why are in the left and the right half symmetric like there are two atoms that go in the middle
Yeah
So it is asymmetric because this is asymmetric
But that would be same
You never know
Look this is the offshore distance
So it is a measure of how close the two atoms get and how far away they go
It is not whether I am making the lecture right
I hope that is clear
I am saying I have got an aggregator number of atoms
Which come and condense at a distance r
You never know
Tell me what happens at a distance r
That is what this diagram is
I don't know
This is the continuous
I think this is the urgent
This is the region
Right
N refers to the number of atoms that is
Nobody asked me that question
Well that comes
. . . . . 다
These back lines?
These ones?
So this is just a distance at which
virtual silicon does not have a band.
The property of the material at that particular distance.
It is just that if I left things B,
it would never condense into this form.
But you could say
that by going by the definition of metal
that a silicon that condenses it
with this interatomic distance
would act as a metal.
Is this enough?
So what was N here?
Well, there is no gap.
It depends upon
at what energy you are injecting carriers into it.
If the energy is much below
this level,
then it will be insulated.
If I am injecting anywhere above this,
then that doesn't matter.
But why doesn't silicon exist
in that virtual region,
but it exists after that virtual region?
No, no.
Silicon exists only at this line.
Nowhere else.
Everything else is virtual here.
Okay.
So can I construct silicon
that is an iron
and a fiber?
See,
first of all,
the further away I go from this black line,
the harder it becomes to construct that.
Right?
Everybody will give me that?
So even if I do strained air epitaxy,
I am not going to go very far away
from that black line.
So whether you can reach that neck region
using strained air epitaxy,
so far there are no reports.
So what was the capital of the drop?
Yeah.
What was the number of?
I don't understand.
.
So another thing,
because of the Williams band being
a collection of
random orbitals
and the conduction band being a collection of
anti-warning orbitals,
at the dashed line,
real silicon,
six n states are in the 3T orbitals.
We can do that.
and 3s has 2n states
because s orbital carries only 2
so there is an asymmetry
in the number of states available
between valence and conduction
in general
that asymmetry will not show itself
because
as we will learn later when we change the x coordinate
of this plot
the energies that are needed to
run into a case where these 2n or 6n
are insufficient
in general it won't arise
the energies needed are just
your silicon crystal will disintegrate
before you get to 2n
so let's say
I start populating these states
how much energy do I need
to actually fill them all up
more than the band gap
because you see these states are in a continuum
which means you need the band gap
energy to reach the band edge
I need more energy to go above that
and that keeps on rising
you will have the exact mathematical formula
for that in a bit
so counting of occupied and unoccupied states
we have done
so now let's define some basics
of what you have learnt regarding band structure
now here is where x coordinates
of that plot become important
I am going to draw
2 different
pictures here
energy
so the previous graph was also in the transformed space
or that was in the non-real space
no that was in real space
I was in real space
this is now in transformed space
I am going to that
so you see E versus R
there is another way of actually plotting this
that is in dual space
E versus A
now this is where x coordinates become dual space
what question is this plot
what information does this plot give you
what is the energy of my electron
versus the separation between the two atoms
or if I have already got a grain of silicon
I have an electron
I want to track its energy as it pops from atom to atom
right
but the thing is the electron is moving in real space
here
so this is known as
band diagram
it's important to get these terminologies right
that's what a band diagram is
this one is in dual space now
E versus K
this still
if I ask myself the same question
the information I would get from this particular
you know
plot would be
how much energy does my electron have
depending on how fast it is moving
so what is the energy of the electron?
not always
I'll show you in a moment
this plot assumes that the band
I should put a name over here
this particular plot is known as
band structure
so band diagram and band structure have two different means
only if I'm very very close to the minimum of the conduction band
and I'll define that in a moment
the further away I go that's no longer true
okay
now let's talk about a direct band gap semiconductor
so it is traditional to locate the top of the valence band at equal to zero
okay
and we always draw this as well as this
for increasing electron energies
okay
this is a convention
you can do it in any other way
by the way it will be perfectly correct
but you will have to add negative signs throughout your entire semiconductor
everywhere
see it's like a voltage right?
if you multiply this with charge
I actually get something that has the dimensions of a voltage