I can either say that my energy of the electron is minus E times E, because the electron charge is negative,
or I can say, okay, I'm going to forget about that negative sign, because it creates a mess for me,
and I'm going to just write it as E times E.
In semiconductors, we follow the E times E convention.
I don't know of a single textbook or a published piece of scientific literature where people do it the other way around.
But the connection band is drawn at the bottom.
The reason is that we generally associate higher energies with anti-bonding orbitals.
We just learned about that.
And since we actually associate that, we want to retain the idea of electrons being promoted to higher energy levels
as the system being in a higher energy state altogether.
So the convention in some sense is forced.
It comes from that natural requirement.
But there's nothing special about that convention.
It is just that this convention is so universal that it basically becomes a protocol.
Okay.
I locate the top of the Willans band at E equal to zero.
If I draw my band diagram now for real silicon, to that dashed line that you had,
my Willans band energy,
would be constant as a function of R.
Why?
I am in the middle of the bulk silicon, right?
My band gap should not change.
I'm inside the same material.
Would you put X mark over here?
Hm?
You are pulling an X mark over here.
I'm just giving you one part of it.
You'll see how radically different this is.
Sure.
Yeah.
So can we say that when I am having, say, in a continuous space,
I have two atoms, A and B,
even if I am changing their relative distance,
A and B and all such atoms exist at a distance that nature intended them to.
Yes.
So that means that distance is now fixed at five amps from the surface area.
So when we are actually varying R, we are just actually changing the reference at the end.
The coordinate of the electron that is free to move around.
That's the purpose of this particular part.
So R is the position of electron relative to the atoms?
Any arbitrarily chosen atom.
Because R equals zero in this case is not special.
It's somewhere in the semiconductor.
So where do we get to draw this diagram for ?
Well, it's useful for calculating electron energies because that's all that we are doing here.
So how do the electron energies distribute themselves?
Both this and this .
But there are different complementary pictures of that.
That's the question.
Okay.
So band-iron, yes.
Atom, you are talking about real silicon here.
We are looking at the R coordinate of the electron.
An electron that is free to move around.
Now if it is in the valence band, it's not free to move around.
It has the same energy no matter where you go in it.
Yes.
That is completely different from that.
That R is different from this R.
This is real silicon.
That was real silicon along a line and then all possible mathematical possibilities of that silicon.
There was a distance between the two silicon atoms.
Here is the position vector of the electron.
Is the position vector of the electron chosen from some other starting point?
Okay.
So the energy that I need to remain in the valence band,
the highest energy at which I remain in the valence band is the same regardless of where I am in the bulb.
Right?
That's my bonding energy.
Similarly, the energy,
the minimum energy at which the electron becomes free to move
is also the same regardless of where you are in the bulb.
So the band diagram is actually pretty simple.
It's two parallel lines.
Everybody understood that?
So can you explain the top line?
This is E C.
This is E V.
But you said that E C varies as we go higher and higher in the conduction band.
So there will be some bands here but we are not showing them.
We are showing the lowest possible energy where the electron can become free.
This is the band gap.
This distance is the band gap.
Any electron which is deeper in the bulb would have to go higher.
It would have to pick up more energy or move more.
Why don't we show the valence band and which is more negative,
the deeper we go into the valence band?
Yes.
So within the bulb,
for the electron is more or less the same.
That is what this diagram is.
That is the definition of bulk is.
Yes, so that is what the diagram is.
So the diagram is implicitly saying that every point in the bulb is equivalent.
That is only for the bulb.
At the surface, things change.
We won't do that.
You might say this is a pretty boring diagram.
Why bother with this at all?
It's just two parallel lines.
The thing is devices don't consist of a single bulb.
It consists of various things that are other than the bulb.
Other materials that they interface may be two contacts or whatever.
In which case,
this diagram would actually have discontinuities at both places.
And then,
now I would become special by the way.
Because how close or far away the electron is from that particular interface makes a difference.
But in the bulb,
it makes no difference whatsoever.
Okay, now let's talk about K,
which is a bit more interesting.
Sir, suppose if we had any subband like above EC and below EV,
what would that jump indicate,
let's say,
EV1 and EV3?
That would just indicate that
this electron,
let's say somewhere there,
is more strongly bound to the iron force,
it is less likely to ever get promoted to being a free electron.
Like an L-shell electron, for instance.
So could it become free by just jumping into EC?
Yeah.
So then what is the significance of that EC button?
EC is the lowest energy at which it can become free.
So where it would go to?
It would go to that same conduction band?
It will go to the conduction band,
or it could go to a point higher than that.
There would be other subband to this side as well.
That is very much different from this one.
They have different energies,
they have different mobilities.
I will define that later.
I spoke to some people.
.
I think somebody was saying parabolas here, so we do that only takes place near the edge
of the conduction band and we are in right there, so when you go far away it won't capture
the number of parabolas.
So I am drawing the conduction band now and this is where the real difference in silicon
and other materials become different.
Why does the energy decrease?
No, energy increases.
Energy increases because remember we are drawing this diagram for increasing electron energies,
conduction band.
In the valence band also the energies increase downwards.
That means it is more strongly bound.
But something else is less strongly bound and I have not defined that something else.
So an electron down here will be more strongly bound.
Sir, but then you know.
When it is more strongly bound why is the momentum more for that?
I will define this momentum in a bit and then it will become clear.
The momentum is not your normal momentum, it is what is known as the crystal momentum
but it is okay.
Sir, so if I say that if I am moving towards the bulk or away from the bulk then only my
k will change, right?
Because when I am moving along the bulk why should my…
Let me define k.
I am not defining k for you here.
What are the really important points?
See, here I did not need to define r because everything was constant, right?
And how many of you have watched Star Trek?
One, two.
You know the queue?
You remember that episode where they have that infinite road?
The road never ends.
That is basically the r existence.
It is very, very boring.
Everything is the same everywhere.
Okay.
This is a little bit different.
So this is the k.
This is the k.
So this is a valence band.
Now I define something known as first breline zone.
I will write it down here so that you guys can know this.
First.
Okay?
First breline zone, FEEZ.
denken WOMAN 2
This is the distance along positive k. By the way, this diagram is going to become significantly
more complicated. Right one is very simple. It's k in this direction, but we'll make it
more complicated in a bit. This is the distance of periodicity. This is the g vector that
we were referring to when we first started talking about dual space. This is the mod
of the g vector. Now, beyond this space, this diagram repeats itself. Now you understand
how this k thing is constructed? Each refers to a unit cell in k space. How do you define
a unit cell in k space? I think the unit cell in real space carry over its Fourier
transform or x-ray diffraction or whatever you have, and then you write down the corresponding
reciprocal relations here. Okay? So in that, as I get further and further away from the
center of the unit cell, my momentum naturally increases. Because what's my natural tendency?
You know, for a bound electron.
Stay within, you know, the bound state. Why do you need to go too far?
So could you please repeat what you used to say?
So as long as I have a bound electron, I have a certain punishment involved in trying to
stray too far away from my bound state. There's an energy barrier to overcome. So I need a
higher and higher momentum to actually overcome that. To pick up enough speed. In some sense,
you've got a neutron star and then there is a planet that is in its gravity. It requires
a lot of energy to get out. It's something similar to that.
Okay. Now how do I draw the conduction band? And this is where there's a little bit of
a head-scratching moment. Have you heard of things called direct and indirect bandgap
semiconductors? No? Okay. This diagram is what really defines that. I'll need to find
that. Just motivate this discussion.
If, if, notice the word if. My conduction band looks like this. If, where the bottom
of the conduction band and the top of the band are at the same k coordinate, chosen
to be k equal to zero for simplicity, then I have a direct bandgap semiconductor. Silicon
is not a direct bandgap semiconductor.
If the bottom of my conduction band and the top of my valence band are at the same k coordinate,
which we choose for convenience to be k equal to zero, then I have a direct bandgap semiconductor.
So what this statement says is that this is the bandgap then, because that's the definition
of what bandgap is. Right? Now, for silicon, so this is, should probably be a little bit
confused discussion otherwise.
I go to 0.85 FBZ. 85% of the way to the edge of the unit cell. And I'm not a forward direction
yet. The direction also matters. That complication will come later. I go up a distance EGR. From
this point, I draw a vertical line.
Wow.
And look at that point. That's the bottom of the conduction band.
It looks a little bit like this. My drawing is not so great, but yeah. That's silicon band
structure with only two bands. You were saying x coordinate matters.
Yeah, it does matter.
Okay. Now what does this mean practically? I'm just going to close with this example.
Which is basically answer a technological question for you. How do LEDs work?
Inject an electron and inject a counter carrier, which I'm going to call a hole in a lecture
or two. They recombine and they get a photon up. If k is momentum, this carrier at this
is the bottom of the conduction band here. And this electron, which is at the top of
the valence band here, has different momentum. How different? 0.85 FBZ. Your FBZ is the unit
of momentum. Okay?
Yes.
What is the momentum of a photon?
H by 3.
Momentum. Not energy.
H by lambda.
Energy divided by C, right?
Yes.
What is C?
Speed of light.
How much? 2.992.
Very large number. So what is the momentum of a photon?
Close to 0. Right? Now, okay. I've got one particle here, one particle here. I want to
combine them and create another particle known as a photon. I must have energy conservation,
but I must also have momentum conservation.
Yes.
So, let's say an electron at momentum k have a basically, it's a hole, but okay,
a counter carrier at momentum 0.
Okay.
Net momentum of the initial state is what? 0.85 FBZ.
Half of it.
Final state is the photon, which has an energy 0 momentum.
Oh.
I can't satisfy that equation. That is the reason why silicon does not make good LEDs.
It goes back, it is basically the corollary of that thing I told you about earlier, that
silicon can be used to do some things, silicon will be used to do some things. This is an
example of the silicon cannot be used to do some things. This is why people bother about
gallium arsenide, gallium nitride and other direct bandgaps and other like this.
So, that's why you use direct conduction band rather than core .
We have to. We have to. How else do we use it at some momentum? So, let's figure out
a way how to do that. Let's say that my ideal direct bandgap points would have been here,
but this is silicon, so it is not here. So, I would basically have to find the process
which takes away that momentum from this electron and allows this recombination to take place.
It's a pretty large momentum. And any horizontal transitions on this actually refer to something
I mentioned right at the beginning of this lecture, they refer to as phonons. Now, if
semiconductors have to do something like this.
So, if you have phonons with large energies available to 0.85 xz, this process would
happen. But phonon energies in most semiconductors are actually very, very small. They are in
milli electron volts, not electron volts either. Yes.
Sir, we could also like feasibly maybe combine like an electron along a vertical
grid. Is that also considered unfeasible? So, you see, if I extend this band further
by the way. Is that energy considered unfeasible? That energy is very, very high.
Okay.
I mean, yes, you could get like extreme UV emission or something, a deep UV emission
from silicon, but the efficiency would be so poor that it would not be worth making it.
So, anyhow, we will continue this very interesting discussion next time.
.